- Question: "Identify two ways through which archaeologists obtain information on the history of Kenya"
  Answer:
    - "Locating pre-historic sites."
    - "Excavating/digging the site."
    - "Dating the fossils and artefacts."
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 1

- Question: "Name one sub-group of Eastern Cushites"
  Answer:
    - "Borana"
    - "Somali"
    - "Oromo"
    - "Gabra"
    - "Rendele"
    - "Burji"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 2

- Question: "Identify the title given to council of elders among the Agikuyu"
  Answer:
    - "Kiama"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 3

- Question: "Give two missionary societies that operated in Kenya"
  Answer:
    - "Catholic missionary societies."
    - "Church missionary society"
    - "Church of Scotland mission"
    - "African inland mission"
    - "The Presbyterian church of Scotland mission"
    - "United Methodist church mission"
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 4

- Question: "Give one way in which African communities in Kenya reacted to British Invasion"
  Answer:
    - "Resistance"
    - "Collaboration"
    - "Mixed reaction"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 5

- Question: "Identify the main reason why kipande system was introduced in Kenya during the Colonial period"
  Answer:
    - "To ensure Africans provide free labor and don’t desert their employers/settlers/servants"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 6

- Question: "Give two challenges faced by independent schools in Kenya"
  Answer:
    - "Harassment of members by missionaries and colonial government authorities."
    - "Shortage of manpower to manage their activities."
    - "Shortage of funds to implement their programs"
    - "Wrangling between leaders."
    - "Competition from missionary churches and schools."
    - "Closure of institutions by colonial government during a state of emergency."
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 7

- Question: "Give two reasons why oathing was administered to Mau Mau fighters"
  Answer:
    - "To ensure members remain loyal and honest to the movement."
    - "To inspire courage among fighters."
    - "To unite the members."
    - "To ensure fighters keep the secrets of the movement."
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 8

- Question: "Identify one commission on education constituted during the colonial period"
  Answer:
    - "Phelps stokes commission (1914)"
    - "Fraser commission (1908)"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 9

- Question: "Identify two ways in which the colonial government encouraged settler farming"
  Answer:
    - "The colonial government provided land to the settlers."
    - "The settlers bought land from the colonial government."
    - "The colonial government passed legislations favorable to the settlers"
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 10

- Question: "Name one founder member of Kenya African Democratic Union"
  Answer:
    - "Daniel Rap Moi"
    - "Masinde Mulirio"
    - "Justus ole Tipis"
    - "Ronald Ngala"
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 11

- Question: "Give the main reason why the second Lancaster house conference was convened in 1962"
  Answer:
    - "To craft/come up with a constitution for independent Kenya."
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 12

- Question: "List two ways in which Kenyan citizens exercise direct democracy"
  Answer:
    - "Referendum"
    - "Initiative"
    - "Plebiscite"
    - "Recall"
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 13

- Question: "Outline two functions of the deputy speaker of the National Assembly"
  Answer:
    - "Acts as speaker when the speaker is absent/performs the duties of the speaker when absent."
    - "Chairperson of the committee of the whole house."
    - "Chairs the Liaison committee."
    - "Chairs the members of the chairperson’s panel."
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 14

- Question: "Give one way in which the government has promoted the culture of the people of Kenya since independence"
  Answer:
    - "By encouraging people to take part in traditional dances/music/festivals."
    - "Establishing and preserving cultural centers."
    - "Licensing vernacular radio stations."
    - "Encouraging production and marketing of traditional handwork/crafts."
    - "Establishing the ministry of sports, culture & gender to enhance culture."
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 15

- Question: "State one challenge facing the Harambee spirit in Kenya"
  Answer:
    - "It has been abused by the political elites to buy/compromise voters."
    - "There are complaints of forced contributions against the harambee spirit of volition."
    - "The NARC government barred public servants from engaging in Harambee (2003)."
    - "Encourages class struggle as it has been one way of staging competition between the haves and the have not’s."
  Marks: 1
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 16

- Question: "Give two ways in which one can become a member of the county assembly of Kenya"
  Answer:
    - "Being elected to represent a ward."
    - "Being nominated."
    - "Through election as speaker, an ex-officio member."
  Marks: 2
  Section: A
  QuestionNumber: 17

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) State five reasons which influenced migration of the Cushites into Kenya during the Pre-colonial period"
      Answer:
        - "To escape from internal clan/family conflicts."
        - "Population pressure in their original homeland."
        - "Fleeing outbreaks of diseases that affected both animals and people."
        - "In search of better grazing lands."
        - "Escaping famine and drought."
        - "Fleeing due to constant attacks from their neighbors e.g. Somali."
        - "Migration to satisfy their spirit of adventure."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(b) Describe the social organization of the Mijikenda during the pre-colonial period"
      Answer:
        - "Family was the smallest social unit."
        - "Initiation of both boys and girls through circumcision."
        - "Circumcised boys joined age sets."
        - "Belief in God called Mulungu."
        - "Direct prayers to God and offerings in shrines."
        - "Belief in ancestral spirits appeased through sacrifices and libations."
        - "Special people like diviners, prophets/wafisi, and medicine men with different social functions."
        - "Polygamous and exogamous marriage."
        - "Social ceremonies marked with songs and dance."
        - "Division of labor by gender and age."
        - "Informal education offered."
      Marks: 10
  QuestionNumber: 18
  Marks: 15
  Section: B

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Give five reasons that enabled the Akamba to successfully participate in the Long Distance trade"
      Answer:
        - "Centrally positioned between the Coast and the interior."
        - "Infertile land leading to trade as an alternative."
        - "Strong leaders organizing trade caravans e.g. Chief Kivoi."
        - "Readily available trade goods."
        - "Participation in Local trade providing experience."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain five factors that influenced the growth of Nairobi as an urban centre"
      Answer:
        - "Central location between Lake Victoria and the Coast."
        - "Conducive climate/cool temperatures."
        - "Trading activities between the Masai and the Agikuyu."
        - "Clean and cool waters from R. Nairobi."
        - "Transfer of colonial headquarters from Mombasa."
        - "Level ground conducive for tall buildings."
      Marks: 10
  QuestionNumber: 19
  Marks: 15
  Section: B

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) State five roles of Africans in the provision of health services during colonial rule in Kenya"
      Answer:
        - "Trained as practitioners e.g. nurses and laboratory assistants."
        - "Treated illnesses using herbal medicine."
        - "Local Native Councils allocated money for medical care."
        - "Promoted hygiene through pest control."
        - "Provided civic education about health and hygiene, controlling some diseases."
        - "Africans built health facilities e.g. dispensaries."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain five roles of women in the Mau Mau uprising during the struggle for Independence in Kenya"
      Answer:
        - "Participated in oath-taking ceremonies."
        - "Mobilized men and women to join the movement."
        - "Composed motivating songs and ridiculed collaborators."
        - "Acted as spies for Mau Mau fighters."
        - "Supplied fighters with essentials like food, medicine, guns, and clothing."
        - "Fought as soldiers e.g. field marshal Muthoni."
        - "Coordinated rural networks for supplying fighters."
        - "Secrecy in protecting uprising information from colonial agents."
        - "Detained and prevented from helping fighters."
      Marks: 10
  QuestionNumber: 20
  Marks: 15
  Section: B

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) State five reasons for the Maasai collaboration"
      Answer:
        - "Weakening of Nandi power."
        - "Civil wars between Kwavi & Purko."
        - "Natural calamities e.g. smallpox & drought."
        - "Famine."
        - "Kedong massacre that killed many."
        - "Efficiency of British reporting on the Massacre."
      Marks: 5
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain five challenges facing culture and sports in Kenya since independence"
      Answer:
        - "Inadequate facilities."
        - "Poor remuneration."
        - "Exploitation in royalty payments."
        - "Inadequate funds for cultural festivities."
        - "Piracy of local artists' work."
        - "Misappropriation of funds/corruption."
        - "Nepotism in team/player selection."
        - "Lack of established structures for nurturing talents."
      Marks: 10
  QuestionNumber: 21
  Marks: 15
  Section: B

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Give three factors that promote National Unity"
      Answer:
        - "Unitary constitution."
        - "One government."
        - "The institution of the presidency."
        - "Our education system."
        - "Economic growth with equitable distribution of resources."
        - "Use of English and Kiswahili."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain six importance of National Integration"
      Answer:
        - "Promotes rapid social and economic development in a country."
        - "Promotes peaceful co-existence of different ethnic groups and races."
        - "Helps eliminate suspicion and enhances security."
        - "Enables a country to develop a national direction."
        - "Enables people to tackle problems together."
        - "Enhances political stability in the country."
        - "Promotes collective responsibility among citizens."
        - "Strengthens a unified voice in international forums."
        - "Attracts foreign investments."
        - "Earns recognition and participation in international activities."
      Marks: 12
  QuestionNumber: 22
  Marks: 15
  Section: C

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) Identify three special groups given special rights in the Kenya Constitution 2010"
      Answer:
        - "Persons with disabilities."
        - "The Youth."
        - "Minorities and Marginalized."
        - "Older members of the society."
        - "Arrested persons."
        - "Persons detained, held in custody or imprisoned."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain six functions of the Kenya National Human Rights and Equality Commission (KNHREC)"
      Answer:
        - "Promote respect for human rights and develop a culture of human rights."
        - "Promote gender equality and equity, coordinate gender mainstreaming."
        - "Promote the protection and observance of human rights in institutions."
        - "Monitor, investigate, and report on human rights observance."
        - "Receive and investigate complaints about alleged human rights abuse."
        - "Investigate or research human rights matters."
        - "Ensure compliance with human rights treaties and conventions."
        - "Investigate improper conduct in public administration."
        - "Investigate complaints of abuse of power or unfair treatment."
        - "Report results of investigations in state affairs."
      Marks: 12
  QuestionNumber: 23
  Marks: 15
  Section: C

- Question: "Answer the following questions"
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "(a) State three sources of revenue for the National Government"
      Answer:
        - "Income tax/PAYE."
        - "Corporate tax."
        - "Capital gain."
        - "Customs duty."
        - "Excise duty."
        - "Export duty."
        - "Value Added Tax (VAT)."
        - "Traffic revenue tax."
        - "Investment revenue from parastatals."
        - "Trading licenses."
        - "Loan interest receipts."
        - "Land rates."
        - "House rates."
        - "Fees."
        - "Court fines."
        - "Tourism fees."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "(b) Explain six ways in which the constitution regulates public finance and expenditure"
      Answer:
        - "Parliament approval of state department expenditure."
        - "Cabinet Secretary for Finance can stop fund transfers without approval."
        - "Controller of Budget oversees budget implementation."
        - "Accounting officers accountable to National Assembly."
        - "Auditing of accounts to ensure procedure adherence."
        - "Auditor General audits government and state organs' accounts."
        - "Public Procurement and disposal act sets procurement procedures."
        - "Sanctions against non-compliant contractors."
        - "Sanctions for tax evasion."
        - "Public advertisement of government contracts."
        - "Establishment of Ethics and Anti-corruption Commission."
        - "Government officers need to prove expenditure."
      Marks: 12
  QuestionNumber: 24
  Marks: 15
  Section: C
